Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today
we're going to be learning about
the concentration of solutions.
So, when it comes to a solution, when
we are trying to concentrate all about
this, we are trying to think all about
how much solute there is dissolved within
the solution, which feels like it can
be one of the most complex topics in
chemistry, but it just boils down to
just trying to understand some of your
basic fractions and be able to label
all of your parts very, very clearly.
when we're trying to understand
what these are representing.
Let's go through it and try to
see if I can make this make a
little bit more sense for you.
So the whole idea comes down to is
whenever we're trying to think about
concentrations is that it's the
amount of solute divided by either a
volume or a mass and that's generally
representing the whole or whatever the
bigger component is within the solution.
Now, why is this super useful?
And it's because solutions are
concentrated or dilute, meaning
that the amount of moles of a
molecule in the liquid will vary.
And we have to be able to understand and
be able to represent that accurately.
So that way, you know what exactly you're
dealing with inside of the workforce.
And or even within just the lab
when you are, when you're learning
all about all this material.
So as we kind of start to go through
this, we will be learning about all these
different types and to explore this of
the three major types of concentration.
So let's take a look at this and stay
tuned to see what this is all about.
So with concentration,
there are three major units.
There are percents.
So with the percents, that's
always the part over the whole.
Now, when it comes to a percent
solution, we can represent this
a couple of different ways.
Well, being that a percent is out of 100,
we can either say it could be the mass of
the solute over the mass of the solution.
It could be the mass of the solute
over the volume of the solution, mass
of, or the volume of the solute over
the volume of the solution as well.
There are multiple ways to show this.
In this video, we're going
to focus on m over m.
And then we will also do one example
of mass over volume to show that
as well, to illustrate two of the
more major types that you will
see in introductory chemistry.
There's also molality.
So molality is a very useful term for
describing colligative properties, which
is how much if you add like a salt to
water, how much does it lower the freezing
point or even raise a boiling point?
that's it.
So it's something that has an effect
on those properties and then molarity,
which is probably the most common
way that we show concentrations in
chemistry, uh, where we always like
to show how concentrated acids and
bases are and different solutions
that you're going to be dealing with.
So we're going to go through each
one, go through example problems.
and be able to work them out to show
you exactly how to work with these.
I have all the chapters marked down below.
So if you're trying to look for a
very specific one, you can go look
for that specific, specific area to
help you pass your chemistry course.
All right, let's take a look into our
first one, which will be in percent.
When it comes to percent solutions, why
is this so important is because this is
one of the most common ways we tend to
illustrate the concentrations of solutions
in biology in the healthcare profession.
So percents, we have to remember
exactly what that means.
So if you need help with percents,
please refer to my percent
video in my math tutorial area.
So percents was always
meaning per percent.
Cent, meaning per 100.
So think a cent, century, cents as
in the money is all about out of 100.
So meaning what is our 100 in this
case is referring to the whole.
So we refer to mass percents as the
amount of the over the whole being that
we're going to focus on mass percents.
How exactly can we show
that in terms of solutions?
Well, the part in this
case is your solute.
So whatever is being dissolved
within your solution.
So let's say if I have some water and
I sprinkle sodium chloride in there,
sodium chloride will be the solute.
Now the solution on the other hand is a
little more complicated than that because
it's not the same thing as the solvent.
Remember, solute, solvent, and
solution are all different terms.
So when we are looking at these, right,
solute was the minor part, the solution
is equal to the solute plus the solvent.
So it's the mass of both of
those components added together
because it's the part of the over
the whole entire picture, right?
So let's take a look at how we
can actually utilize this in an
example for working with percents.
So just remember part over the whole.
All right, what is the mass percent
of a solution made of 5 grams
of NaCl and 95 grams of water?
So as I just said, part over the whole.
So what we have to do is
just label our two parts.
So what is our solute in this case?
That is going to be the minor component
or whatever is the smaller bit.
And now we also have our solvent as well.
So we want to stay organized when
we are working with these problems.
So being that we have our solute, that's
going to be five grams of NaCl, and
that's going to be on top of our fraction.
And the whole in this case is going to
be our solvent, so 95 grams of water.
But keep in mind, it's
over the entire thing.
So the solvent isn't everything, right?
The solute is a big chunk.
So we're going to take this 5 grams
of NaCl, add them to the 95 grams of
water to make our entire solution.
So that way, when we do 5 plus
95, it's going to equal 100.
So what we will do is do 5 divided by 100
times 100%, and what we are going to get
is a 5 percent by mass solution of NaCl.
So, and it's very typical
to put 5 percent NaCl.
But if you want to specify what type of
percentage that is, that's always useful
information to know for a reader as well.
But usually we'll just say 5 percent NACL
when we are showing that information.
Now keep in mind, this is one of the
most popular when it comes to biology,
especially in the healthcare field
because you think of IVs, saline
solutions, glucose solutions that
you might be giving to patients are
typically represented in percents.
So if you ever see an IV,
they always say about 0.
9 percent of NACL is how much you're
giving, which is the standard, or about 5
percent of glucose, which is the standard
amount of sugar for most patients.
So you usually see these represented
in percent, so you have to understand
what do they represent so you are
giving the correct IVs to your patients.
Solution is prepared by dissolving 2.
214 grams of NACL in 246 grams of water.
What is the mass percent?
So once again we have another very
similar problem to the one we had before,
but instead everything is still and is
also being represented in very large
units of grams and of per water as well.
So when we are trying to represent these
as conversion factors and we're given
the percent and put them over 100, But
being that they are just a fraction, you
can still represent them under whatever
the two pieces are to added together.
So we are still gonna do the same
process that we did before, right?
We have our solute, we're gonna put
that on the top and the bottom to make
our part and our hole in this case.
So we have our part, which is
the 2.2146 uh grams of NACL.
We're going to add that to water,
which is 246 grams of water.
And that's going to be times 100%.
Keep in mind when you're doing these
in your calculator, I would recommend
putting the bottom in parentheses.
So that way it does the math correctly.
It's really easy to just type,
plug it away and you'll get 2.
24214, we'll divide 2.
214 and cancel out.
So you'll get like 1 over
246 and get a crazy number.
That's not going to make sense.
So when you do all this, what
you're going to get is, uh, 0.
892 percent of NACL, which is how
much solution you need to prepare if
you were trying to do this in LEP.
Let's take a look at how this would
be used as a conversion factor.
So, as I was mentioning earlier, this
can be used as a conversion term too.
It's not just limited to figuring
out, okay, what's the concentration?
We might use it as well.
Um, so if I said a solution
is 25 percent sodium chloride,
how many grams of solution are
needed to have 15 grams of NaCl?
So if you want to give a
reaction 15 grams NaCl, how much
solution do you need to add?
So, with these, what's really
important is to make sure you kind
of, uh, label and organize all these
really important little pieces.
So we have the 25 percent by mass
of NACL, and then we also have
the 15 grams of NACL here as well.
So, these are types of problems we
have practiced before in other videos.
Um, especially when you're
defining percent out of 100.
So what you can always assume is when you
have a percent, is being that this is by
mass, you can say that this is 25 grams
of NaCl over 100 grams of your solution.
So you can do this for any sample.
You can do it in empirical formulas.
You can do it in concentrations.
This has been used all over the place.
We also have that we have
15 grams of NaCl as well.
So what exactly are we looking for?
What is our desired?
Well, it wants to know is how many
grams of solution are there in this?
Which as you can see, that's
our unit here at the bottom.
So what we need to do is,
what can we start with?
Well, we can start with the
conversion term, which is on
the left, or a term by itself.
It's always easier to start with
a term by itself because you
cannot take an inverse of it.
You can leave it just
the way it is in Chem.
So we'll start with 15 grams of NACL.
We'll plug in 25 grams NACL.
And that's equivalent to
100 grams of solution.
And what we can now do is we'll see
is our units are going to cancel.
And this is going to leave us
only with grams of solution,
which is exactly what we want.
So we'll do 15 times
100, divide that by 25.
And what we are going to get is
there's going to be 60 grams of
solution that we will need to
add for our chemical reaction.
And that is our correct answer.
Let's take a look at our next type of
concentration, molality, which is moles
of solute over kilograms of solvent.
Now typically this is referred to
with water because we're always
using this to describe something
called colligative properties.
Now being that this is molality, so
with an extra L in it, so I highlighted
that in white, it's represented by an
italic M, so kind of like a cursive M.
When you are drawing this, so whenever
we have a one M, this is referred to as
a molal, which is how you pronounce that.
So if you want to know how many
molals you have, you have, if
you have one, you have one molal.
So this is exclusively used generally
to describe colligative properties.
And that's because solutions,
they vary with temperature.
So one thing that we're going to, that
you, that you will learn about is that.
If the temperature changes, the volume
of your solution is going to change with
it because the more that these molecules
are getting excited, the more they're
going to essentially exhibit a pressure.
So being that volume can change,
this is why we use molality
because it kind of circumvents that
whole entire reliability on it.
It goes purely off the masses, which
will not change with the conditions.
Now, molality is also a term
that's generally some more of an
older term because it was more
used when, let's say, central air
conditioning and central, central
cooling was not as readily available.
So, you will start, you kind of see
it's getting phased more and more out.
But it is very heavily used still
especially when referring to colligative
properties, which is how a solute changes
things like boiling point and freezing
point and osmosis and all the and all
these other really important concepts.
So let's try to use some, try to
solve for this in some calculations.
Calculate the molality of sucrose
solution made by dissolving 42.
03 grams of Of Sucrose and 62.
03 grams of water and I have
the formula there to help us.
So the first thing that we have to
do when we're trying to solve this
one is identify what our solute is.
So being that water is the minor
or not water, sorry, Sucrose
is the minor component here.
This is our solute.
So what we have to do is convert
that to moles of our solute.
So what we will do is we have 42.
03 grams of sucrose.
In order to convert that to
moles, we have to use the molar
mass, which I provided here.
So, and usually for molecules this big,
it typically is provided, but not always.
So if it's provided, great, makes it easy.
So we have 342 grams of sucrose,
and that's going to be equivalent
to one mole of sucrose.
And what we are going to see is that
grams of sucrose cancels grams of sucrose.
Leaving us with just moles.
So now when we are to do that,
what we are going to end up
getting is 0.1228 moles of sucrose.
Now are we done the problem?
Well, as you kind of look up
before, we have to divide that
number by kilograms of solvent.
So we have 62.03 grams of water.
So we gotta go from grams to kilograms.
Which if you can remember, 1, 000 grams
is equivalent to 1 kilogram from prefixes.
Let's take that number that we
found out from before and divide
it by our water in kilograms.
So we have 0.
1228 moles, and we're
going to divide that by 62.
03, which is how much water was
in the original problem above.
So we have 62.
03.
Grams, and we're going to convert that
to kilograms in our fraction here.
So let's kind of set
that up for ourselves.
So we're going to put a little
mini dimensional analysis
here in the denominator.
So 1000 grams is one kg.
So what this will be is 0.
1228 and essentially
that'd be divided by 62.
03 divided by 1000.
So when we solve for that, what
we will get Is 1.98 mole, and
we'll put that in that cursive M
and that refers to 1.98 moles of
sucrose over one kilogram of water.
Okay?
So, and that is how we would solve
this problem here is just like that.
Let's go on to another
example using modality.
If the modality of KCL is five mole.
How many ions does KCl break
into when it's dissolved?
And then I asked, what is the
total molality of the solution?
So this is a two parter.
So KCl, how does that dissolve?
So it goes off your solubility rules
in understanding how all that works.
So if I have KCl, which is aqueous,
that's going to break down into our
cation and our anion, which are K plus.
and Cl minus, right?
So how many ions do you have?
Well, looking at that, you
have one, two ions total.
So what does that refer to?
Well, that refers to the second
part of the problem, which
asks for the total molality.
Now, one thing about molality, it
refers to how many ions are in solution.
It's about colligative properties,
which is all about how ions
affect different properties.
So one thing that gets affected
is depending on how many ions
there are, that concentrate, that
concentration above can change.
So there's five molal of KCl,
but the total is essentially
times the number of ions.
So if I have two ions in solution, What
I'm going to simply do is times that
by 5 molal, and that's going to equal a
total of 10 molal, or the total molality
for all ions in the solution, and that's
because it dissociated it into two pieces.
So if you had something that's
associated into three pieces,
you would times it by three, four
pieces of times by four and so on.
So it's all about how many ions
that are in, in the actual solution.
So it's a pretty easy concept,
but it's kind of strange just
because it's, it's different than
any of the other concentrations.
Um, so it's all about
the ions specifically.
Let's look at our last
type of concentration.
Our last type of
concentration is molarity.
Which, what molarity is, so molarity, so
with the R focused this time, so the L,
it's the amount of moles of the solute
over the volume of solution, so it's
all about the liquid side of it instead.
So, now why is this one so important?
It's probably, it's arguably
the most common concentration
that's used in a chemistry lab.
So if you have to use this in, for
future chemistry classes, so with general
chemistry, analytical chemistry, physical,
organic, you will be using this a lot.
So I recommend mastering it and
getting comfortable with it.
I have a two follow up videos for this,
which is on molarity itself and a dilution
video to help emphasize this concept.
So now when it comes to using it,
let's try to practice using the formula
and getting comfortable with it.
So if I have an intravenous or an
IV saline solution and it's being
administered to a patient in the
hospital, one saline solution contains 0.
898 grams of sodium chloride.
In 525 milliliters of
solution, what is the molarity?
So from earlier, it was moles over liters.
So and that's the most
important thing to remember.
Remember big M is moles over liters, which
is going to be used a lot in this course.
So if we are to use this, the
first thing we need to do is
convert our moles to liters.
So what we have is grams of NaCl, and
I'm going to convert that to molarity.
So by using the molar mass of NaCl.
So the molar mass of NaCl is 58.
44.
So let's write that down.
So 58.
44 grams.
And that's equivalent to one mole of NaCl.
Now, after we write that, we are
going, we notice that all of our units
cancel, which is really good for us.
We want that to happen.
So that way it ends up putting
it all in the correct units.
So now that we have that down,
we can see that, okay, that's
going to be equivalent to 0.
moles of NaCl.
Now for that, what we are
going to now do is divide that
by the liters of our solvent.
So, up above, we see that
we have 525 milliliters.
So to convert that to liters, we'll
divide that number by 1000, making it 0.
525.
If we were to finish this, so what we
will do is we will take this number,
we'll copy it, divide this by 0.
525 liters,
and what we are going
to get in return is 0.
0293 molarity.
Now, this is a very,
very small concentration.
So when you have smaller concentrations,
Usually in introductory chem,
we represent it just with big M
molarity, just to keep it simple.
But if you are in a more advanced
class, it is very common to show
this in millimoles or milli molarity.
So we just refer to as millimoles.
So if that's to happen, uh, what
you would do is you'd, you would
essentially, uh, times this number
by a thousand and you would get 29.3.
millimoles as a concentration as well.
So just so you're aware for anyone
else that might be watching this
and using this for their course.
Um, some instructors use it very commonly.
I use it from time to time
for smaller concentrations.
So just so you're aware, let's
go on to using this not only
to solve for concentration.
But, this is one of the most commonly
used stoichiometry of conversion
factors that's used as well.
Let's look at our last example.
When we're, when we're converting
concentrations, we saw using percents,
that was a very common way of converting,
but molarity is also very commonly used.
So why not use them both together?
So what is a mol, what is the molarity
of a 6 percent solution of NaCl?
And this, and I want you
to assume the density is 0.
995 grams per milliliter.
So how would we do this?
So we got to think for molarity,
what was that con, what was
that the symbols for that?
The big M was equal to moles all over
liters being that we have the percent
above, so we have this percent here.
Let's try to put that
into something useful.
So if you remember it was grams over
solution, well mole Well when it comes
to molarity, that was also moles of
solute over liters of the solution
So they're very similar to each other
in terms of solute and solution.
So with our 6% We have 6 grams
of solute, or NaCl, all over 100
milliliters of our sol or sorry,
100 milliliters of our solution.
Now, we want to convert that to,
or sorry, not 100 milliliters,
we have 100 grams of solution.
So being that is a mass by mass percent.
So how do we get it to milliliters?
Well, we were given the density
here, which can help, which refers
to the density of the solution.
So what we are going to do is convert
the bottom part of the formula first.
So when we do that, we
are going to take our 0.
995 grams, and that's equivalent to
1 milliliter, and that's going to now
cancel grams over grams, but being
that this has to be into liters here.
So if you remember how,
so we need to now convert.
1000 mL to 1 L.
Alright, that's a lot
already, but we're not done.
We have essentially this in the
right volume units, but we need to
convert the grams of NaCl to moles.
So what would be the last step?
How do you go from grams to moles?
When you think about it,
it's molar mass, right?
So the very, very last thing that
you have to do to convert 6 grams
of NaCl to moles is use molar mass.
So if you take 58.
44 grams of NaCl, and that's compared
to 1 mole of NaCl, what these are going
to do is we cancel these terms out, and
that's going to give us moles of NaCl.
A lot.
So how would you put
this in your calculator?
How would you do it?
So if it was me, I would do six divided
by a hundred, it equals, times that by 0.
995, times by a thousand, it
equal, and then divide by 58.
44, and what we are going to
get is a molal, a molarity of 1.
02 big M for our final concentration.
So this is a little bit of a
preview of solution stoichiometry.
Which is very, very readily used
in general chemistry and in the
end of introductory chemistry.
Let's take a look at our final
thoughts and conclusions here.
So as you saw, when it comes to
concentration units, there's a lot, right?
There are several different types
that you need to practice and to go
through and get comfortable with.
And you'll get, and you'll use
a lot of these in lab as well.
So the percents and molality, molarity,
these are all really big concepts.
Now which ones are the most important?
So for you, for your scientific career, if
you are a health science major, percents
are going to be essentially used in
terms of all IVs and a lot of different
drugs that are administered as well in
terms of the pharmaceuticals as well.
You will commonly see percents
used in that capacity.
So getting comfortable with
knowing dosages and how they're
used is a very good skill.
In fact, if you've gone through my
dimensional analysis videos and my math
videos, You have seen these already
and have gotten comfortable with them.
Molality is generally mainly reserved for,
I would say more for science majors who
have to go into harder chemistry courses.
It's not used a ton after the solution
chemistry in terms of, uh, introductory
chem, even in general chemistry,
it's a more of a rarer concentration.
It's good to be aware of it
because it is used, but it is
a little bit on the rare side.
Malarity though is the most
common one in terms of chemistry.
It's used all the time in terms
of concentrations and it's used
in most laboratory settings.
So I would get used to it because
the higher that number is.
The more concentrated it is,
meaning the more moles there are
within a given liter of solution.
So it can be used not, as you can see,
all these are not only concentrations,
but they can be used to convert as well,
which is why they are so important because
they bridge the gap from our goal, which
is always the mole to either liters or
kilograms or all these different units.
Which is extremely important.
Thank you once again
so much for listening.
I hope that this video
helped you a little bit.
I know it was a longer one, but if you
liked it, please hit the like button.
Subscribe to the channel
if you haven't yet.
And if you have any questions
or any suggestions for
future videos, comment below.
I'd love to hear from you.
So thank you all so much.
And if I see you on campus, please
say hi, and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.